Contact

alberto17576@gmail.com

www.linkedin.com/in/albertomartinez-becares-556005134 (LinkedIn) orcid.org/0000-0001-9735-6588 (Other)

Top Skills

Communication

Coaching

Partnerships

Languages

German (Limited Working)
Spanish (Native or Bilingual)
French (Limited Working)
English (Full Professional)

Alberto Martinez-Becares

Group Scientist/Group Head at Procter & Gamble

Brussels Metropolitan Area

Summary

My current responsibilities focus on designing formulated products and processes using digital tools to delight Consumers. In particular the use of data activation methodologies to (eg first principles modelling and data science) to create more, faster and better innovation for P&G consumers. My job comprises integrating data across Consumer, Product and Process functions.

During my 15 years of experience, I have completed different assignments in , Front End Innovation, Process/Manufacturing interface, Product Designer, Data Engineering & Science and Modelling bringing alive new products into the market.

Experience

Procter & Gamble 17 years 2 months

Group Scientist at Procter & Gamble November 2020 - Present (3 years 4 months) Belgium

Lead design of products and processes based on data and models.

Champion data activation in the organization.

Master integrator.

Product Stability in the market.

Lead application of industrial data science & AI to accelerate and transform the way how R&D innovates.

Design of formulated products and processes using both mechanistic models and machine learning.

Quantitative methods for sustainability in Consumer Products.

Lead data governance and stewardship for R&D data systems.

External collaboration with Universities & Public Funding.

Grow and coach data science and modelling citizens in the organization.

Data & Modelling: Python, R, SQL, GitHub, Databricks, JIRA, Power BI, JMP & JMP scripting, KNIME, Posit Connect, COMSOL, Linux

Senior Scientist

July 2010 - Present (13 years 8 months)

Brussels Area, Belgium

Product and process development and design of detergents to meet consumer needs and product stability requirements in the supply chain.

Digitalization of the organization to drive efficiency using modelling and data science capabilities.

Implementation of new digital workflows for R&D using Artificial Intelligence. Global product stability in the market.

Creation of new IP.

Lead Product cost optimization.

Should Cost Analysis of product and process.

Process Analytical Technology(PAT)

Rheology and Dynamical Mechanical Analysis of materials.

Liquid Formulation technology

Liquid Mixing

Color science applied to formulations.

Film technology and film coating.

Liquid Dosing.

External interaction with academics and external research programs.

Qualification of raw materials from suppliers. Product cost optimization.

Data & Modelling: Python , R, SQL, JMP, PowerBI, KNIME, Pipeline Pilot ,

COMSOL, gPROMS, Ansys, SIMCA

Engineer

January 2008 - June 2010 (2 years 6 months)

Newcastle upon Tyne, United Kingdom

Start-up of a new process line for soluble unit dose detergents.

Process development in powder making and converting to improve product quality and process reliability in the plant.

Product Stability design and modelling.

Quality and statistical process control.

Data & Modelling: JMP, Mathcad

Postdoctoral Researcher

January 2007 - December 2007 (1 year)

Newcastle upon Tyne, United Kingdom

Design of formulated products for Automatic Dishwashers.

Powder formulations.

Johannes Kepler University Scientist

October 2004 - December 2006 (2 years 3 months)

Linz, Austria

At the Institute of Process Engineering.

- Design and construct heat exchanger leveraging corrugated pipes for local company.
- Design and construct a heat pipe (CO2) to test different types of heat transfer pipes for local company.
- Measure pump characteristics for external pump manufacturer.
- Teaching and laboratory supervision.
- Research: Design and construct a pilot unit to measure permeability in membranes with liquid and supercritical CO2. Characterization of microfiltration membranes for CO2.

Hamburg University of Technology PHD Student January 2004 - September 2004 (9 months) Harburg, Germany

At the Institute of Thermal Separation Processes.

Design a process for coating of particles with proteins using fluidized beds operated with supercritical CO2.

Education

Universidad de Salamanca

Doctor of Philosophy - PhD, Chemical and Environmental

Engineering · (2000 - 2005)